# JUNLE JIANG

School of Geosciences, Mewbourne College of Earth and Energy University of Oklahoma, Norman, OK 73019

Webpage: https://jjle.github.io

*Email*: jiang@ou.edu *Office*: +1 (405) 325-3253

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am interested in the dynamic processes in the Earth's crust and strive to understand their mechanisms, predictability, and societal impacts, with the ultimate goals to improve the assessment and mitigation of geohazards and safe, sustainable exploration of geo-energy. My current research is focused on microseismicity, large earthquakes, and crustal deformation due to tectonic and human activities over timescales from seconds to centuries, through integrating laboratory-based physical models and geophysical observations, in particular from Global Navigation Satellite System (GNSS) and Interferometric Synthetic Aperture Radar (InSAR).

#### **EDUCATION**

Peking University, Beijing, China	Physics	B.Sc., 2009
Caltech, Pasadena, CA, USA	Geophysics	M.Sc., 2011
Caltech, Pasadena, CA, USA	Computational Science and Engineering	Ph.D. Minor, 2014
Caltech, Pasadena, CA, USA	Geophysics	<i>Ph.D.</i> , 2016

#### **APPOINTMENTS**

Assistant Professor, School of Geosciences, University of Oklahoma	2020/08-present
Postdoctoral Associate, Cornell University	2018/06-2020/07
Green Postdoctoral Scholar, Scripps Institution of Oceanography, UC San Diego	2016/02-2018/05
Research and Teaching Assistant, Seismological Laboratory, Caltech	2009/09-2015/12

#### PHD DISSERTATION

Jiang, J. (2016), Probabilistic Imaging and Dynamic Modeling of Earthquake Source Processes, California Institute of Technology. <a href="doi:10.7907/Z9639MQC">doi:10.7907/Z9639MQC</a>. (Advisors: M. Simons & N. Lapusta)

# PUBLICATIONS IN REVIEW/PREPARATION

- 1. Materna, K., A. Barbour, **J. Jiang**, and M. Eneva, A decade of crustal deformation and aseismic slip at the North Brawley Geothermal Field, under review.
- 2. **Jiang., J.**, B. Erickson, V. Lambert, R. Ando, S. Barbot, C. Cattania, L. Dal Zilio, B. Duan, E. Dunham, A. Gabriel, N. Lapusta, D. Li, M. Li, D. Liu, D. Liu, Y. Liu, S. Ozawa, C. Pranger, Y. van Dinther, Community-driven code comparisons for three-dimensional multiscale modeling of sequences of earthquakes and aseismic slip (SEAS), in preparation for JGR.

#### REFEREED PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **Jiang, J.**, Y. Bock, and E. Klein (2021), Coevolving early afterslip and aftershock signatures of a San Andreas fault rupture, *Science Advances*, 7. doi:10.1126/sciadv.abc1606. Media Coverage: OU News.
- 2. **Jiang, J.**, & Lohman, R. B. (2020). Coherence-guided InSAR deformation analysis in the presence of ongoing land surface changes in the Imperial Valley, California. *Remote Sens. Environ.*, 112160. doi:10.1016/j.rse.2020.112160.
- 3. Erickson, B.\*, **J. Jiang**\*, M. Barall, N. Lapusta, E. M. Dunham, R. Harris, L. Abrahams, K. Allison, J.-P. Ampuero, S. Barbot, C. Cattania, A. Elbanna, Y. Fialko, B. Idini, J. Kozdon, V. Lambert, Y. Liu, Y. Luo, X. Ma, P. Segall, P. Shi, and M. Wei, The Community code verification exercise for simulating sequences of

- earthquakes and aseismic slip (SEAS), Seismo. Res. Lett. (\*equal contributions). doi:10/ggj42s.
- 4. Tymofyeyeva, E., Fialko, Y., **Jiang, J.**, Xu, X., Sandwell, D., Bilham, R., et al (2019). Slow slip event on the southern San Andreas fault triggered by the 2017 Mw8.2 Chiapas (Mexico) earthquake. *J. Geophys. Res. Solid Earth*, 124. doi:10.1029/2018JB016765. Media Coverage: EOS Research Spotlight.
- Xu, X., L. Ward, J. Jiang, B. Smith-Konter, E. Tymofyeyeva, E. Lindsey, A. G. Sylvester, and D. T. Sandwell (2018), Surface creep rate of the Southern San Andreas Fault modulated by stress perturbations from nearby large events, *Geophys. Res. Lett.*, 45, 10259–10268, doi:10.1029/2018GL080137.
- 6. Gombert, B., Z. Duputel, R. Jolivet, M. Simons, **J. Jiang**, C. Liang, E. J. Fielding, and L. Rivera (2018), Strain budget of the Ecuador–Colombia subduction zone: A stochastic view, *Earth Planet. Sci. Lett.*, 498, 288–299, doi:10.1016/j.epsl.2018.06.046.
- 7. Fan, W., D. Bassett, **J. Jiang**, P. M. Shearer, and C. Ji (2017), Rupture evolution of the 2006 Java tsunami earthquake and the possible role of splay faults, *Tectonophysics*, *721*, 143–150, <u>doi:10.1016/j.tecto.2017.10.003</u>.
- 8. Michel, S., J.-P. Avouac, N. Lapusta, and **J. Jiang** (2017), Pulse-like partial ruptures and high-frequency radiation at creeping-locked transition during megathrust earthquakes, *Geophys. Res. Lett.*, *44*, 8345–8351, doi:10.1002/2017GL074725.
- Jiang, J. and N. Lapusta (2017), Connecting depth limits of interseismic locking, microseismicity, and large earthquakes in models of long-term fault slip, *J. Geophys. Res. Solid Earth*, 122, 6491–6523, doi:10.1002/2017JB014030.
- 10. Yue, H., M. Simons, Z. Duputel, **J. Jiang**, E. Fielding, C. Liang, S. Owen, A. Moore, B. Riel, J. P. Ampuero and S.V. Samsonov (2016), Depth varying rupture properties during the 2015 Mw 7.8 Gorkha (Nepal) earthquake, *Tectonophysics*, 714–715, 44-54, doi:10.1016/j.tecto.2016.07.005.
- 11. **Jiang, J.**, and M. Simons (2016), Probabilistic imaging of tsunamigenic seafloor deformation during the 2011 Tohoku-oki Earthquake, *J. Geophys. Res. Solid Earth*, 121, 9050–9076, doi:10.1002/2016JB013760. Media Coverage: EOS Research Spotlight.
- 12. **Jiang, J.**, and Y. Fialko (2016), Reconciling seismicity and geodetic locking depths on the Anza section of the San Jacinto fault, *Geophys. Res. Lett.*, *43*, 10663–10671, doi:10.1002/2016GL071113.
- 13. Bletery, Q., A. Sladen, **J. Jiang.** and M. Simons (2016), A Bayesian source model for the 2004 great Sumatra-Andaman earthquake, *J. Geophys. Res. Solid Earth*, 121, 5116–5135, doi:10.1002/2016[B012911.
- 14. **Jiang, J.**, and N. Lapusta (2016), Deeper penetration of large earthquakes on seismically quiescent faults, *Science*, *352*(6291), 1293–1297, doi:10.1126/science.aaf1496. Media Coverage: New Yorker, Phys.org.
- Duputel, Z., J. Jiang, R. Jolivet, M. Simons, L. Rivera, J.-P. Ampuero, B. Riel, S. E. Owen, A. W. Moore, S. V. Samsonov, F. O. Culaciati, and S. E. Minson (2015), The Iquique earthquake sequence of April 2014: Bayesian modeling accounting for prediction uncertainty, *Geophys. Res. Lett.*, 42, 7949–7957, doi:10.1002/2015GL065402.
- Bletery, Q., A. Sladen, B. Delouis, M. Vallée, J.-M. Nocquet, L. Rolland, and J. Jiang (2014), A detailed source model for the M<sub>w</sub> 9.0 Tohoku-Oki earthquake reconciling geodesy, seismology, and tsunami records, J. Geophys. Res. Solid Earth, 119, 7636–7653, doi:10.1002/2014/B011261.
- 17. Minson, S. E., M. Simons, J. L. Beck, F. Ortega, **J. Jiang**, S. E. Owen, A. W. Moore, A. Inbal, and A. Sladen (2014), Bayesian inversion for finite fault earthquake source models II: the 2011 great Tohoku-oki, Japan earthquake, *Geophys. J. Int.*, 198(2), 922–940. doi:10.1093/gji/ggu170.
- 18. Wei, S., R. Graves, D. V. Helmberger, J.-P. Avouac, and **J. Jiang** (2012), Sources of shaking and flooding during the Tohoku-Oki earthquake: A mixture of rupture styles, *Earth Planet. Sci. Lett.*, *333-334*(C), 91–100, doi:10.1016/j.epsl.2012.04.006.
- Simons, M., S. E. Minson, A. Sladen, F. Ortega, J. Jiang, S. E. Owen, L. Meng, J. P. Ampuero, S. Wei, R. Chu, D. V. Helmberger, H. Kanamori, E. Hetland, A. W. Moore, and F. H. Webb (2011), The 2011 magnitude 9.0 Tohoku-oki earthquake: Mosaicking the megathrust from seconds to centuries, *Science*, 332(6036), 1421–1425, doi:10.1126/science.1206731.

#### **INVITED TALK**

Berkeley Seismological Laboratory Seminar, UC Berkeley	2021/09
Earthquake Science Center Seminar, USGS	2021/07
School of Geosciences, University of Oklahoma	2020/03
Andes Seminar, Department of Earth and Atmospheric Sciences, Cornell University	2019/09
Department of Earth, Atmospheric and Planetary Sciences, Massachusetts Institute of Technology	2019/03
Department of Geology and Geophysics, Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution	2018/03
Department of Earth, Planetary, and Space Sciences, University of California Los Angeles	2017/03
Scripps Institution of Oceanography, University of California, San Diego	2016/03

#### **SELECTED CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS**

Jiang., J., Bock, Y., and E. Klein, Dynamics of early afterslip-aftershock coevolution following the 2004 Parkfield earthquake, SSA Annual Meeting, Apr. 2021 (Oral Presentation).

Jiang, J., and Lohman, R. B., Characterizing tectonic and anthropogenic ground deformation history in the Imperial Valley, California, using Sentinel-1 InSAR time series, AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco, CA, Dec. 2019 (Oral Presentation).

Jiang, J. (2019), Perspectives from the SCEC Sequences of Earthquakes and Aseismic Slip (SEAS) Project, SCEC workshop on "How Physics-Based Earthquake Simulators Might Help Improve Earthquake Forecasts," June 18, 2019 (Invited Oral Presentation).

Jiang, J. (2019), Perspectives from the SCEC Sequences of Earthquakes and Aseismic Slip (SEAS) Project, SCEC workshop on "How Physics-Based Earthquake Simulators Might Help Improve Earthquake Forecasts," June 18, 2019 (Invited Oral Presentation).

Jiang., J., Bock, Y., and E. Klein, Imaging slip evolution on the San Andreas fault due to the 2004 Parkfield earthquake, AGU Fall Meeting, Washington D.C., Dec. 2018 (Oral Presentation).

Jiang, J., and Erickson, B. A. Advancing Simulations of Sequences of Earthquakes and Aseismic Slip (SEAS). SCEC Annual Meeting, Sept. 2018 (Invited Oral Presentation).

Jiang, J. and Y. Fialko, Mechanisms of unsteady shallow creep on major crustal faults, AGU Fall Meeting, New Orleans, LA, Dec. 2017 (Oral Presentation).

Jiang, J., and M. Simons, Multiscale probabilistic imaging of tsunamigenic seafloor deformation during the 2011 Tohoku-oki earthquake, SSA Fall Meeting, Denver, CO, Apr. 2017 (Invited Oral Presentation).

Kirschvink, J. and J. Jiang, Potential Seismic and Tsunami Hazard from the Palau Trench, as viewed from molluscan grazing notches in uplifted coral atolls, GSA Annual Meeting, Oct. 2014 (Oral Presentation).

Jiang, J., Lapusta, N. and H. Noda, Re-evaluating the seismogenic potential of creeping fault regions: implications from models with rate-and-state friction and enhanced coseismic weakening, AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco, CA, USA, Dec. 2013 (Invited Oral Presentation).

# **FUNDED RESEARCH AND WORKSHOPS**

#### **External Research Grants**

PI, 2020 SCEC, \$27,000, "Distinguishing between Tectonic and Anthropogenic Processes in the Salton Sea Geothermal Field."

PI, 2017–2021 XSEDE (Extreme Science and Engineering Discovery Environment) Award with an allocation of 120,000 computing units, "Integrated Simulation of Dynamic Earthquakes and Crustal Deformation."

PI (w/ B. Erickson), 2018/2019/2020 SCEC, \$45,000/\$50,000/\$56,000, "Advancing Simulations of Sequences of Earthquakes and Aseismic Slip (SEAS)."

Co-PI (PI: Y. Fialko), 2018 SCEC, \$28,000, "Mechanisms of unsteady shallow creep on major crustal faults."

Co-PI (PI: Y. Fialko), 2017 SCEC, \$28,000, "Microseismicity, geodetic coupling, and earthquake variability on heterogeneous faults: A case study of the Anza section of the San Jacinto Fault."

Co-PI (PI: Y. Fialko), 2016 SCEC, \$28,000, "Reconciling seismic and geodetic locking depths on the Anza segment of the San Jacinto Fault."

# **Workshop Grants**

PI (w/ B. Erickson), 2020 SCEC, \$12,000, "Workshop for Advancing Simulations of Sequences of Earthquakes and Aseismic Slip (SEAS) — Free-Surface effects in 2D/3D models."

PI (w/ B. Erickson), 2019 SCEC, \$12,000, "Workshop for Advancing Simulations of Sequences of Earthquakes and Aseismic Slip (SEAS) — Full Dynamics and 3D Effects."

PI (w/ B. Erickson), 2018 SCEC, \$12,000, "Workshop for Advancing Simulations of Sequences of Earthquakes and Aseismic Slip (SEAS) — Exploring Complexity and Resolution."

PI (w/ R. Harris, B. Erickson), 2017 SCEC, \$18,500, "A Joint Workshop: Rupture Dynamics Code Validation and Comparing Simulations of Earthquake Sequences and Aseismic Slip."

## **HONORS AND AWARDS**

Green Postdoctoral Fellowship, IGPP, SIO, UCSD 201	5–2018
Caltech Leadership Award, Graduate Student Office, Caltech	2016
Demetriades-Tsafka-Kokkalis Best Thesis Prize in Seismo-Engineering, Prediction, and Protection, Caltech	2016
Chinese Government Award for Outstanding Self-Financed Students Abroad	2015
Outstanding Student Paper Award, Tectonophysics Section, American Geophysical Union	2015
Honor for Excellent Graduate, Peking University	2009
Petro China Scholarship, Peking University	2007
Dean's List Award for Academic Excellence, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology	2007
Cannon Scholarship, Peking University	2006

TEACHING	
Instructor, University of Oklahoma	
GPHY6970 Machine Learning in Geosciences (w/ H. Bedle & M. Pranter; 10 students)	Fall 2021
GPHY5970 Remote Sensing for Crustal Geophysics (6 students)	Fall 2021
GPHY5920 Computational Geophysics (5 students)	Spring 2021
GPHY3440 Mentored Research Experience (1 student)	Spring 2021
GEOL1114 Physical Geology for Scientists and Engineers (37 students)	Fall 2020
Guest Lecturer, Cornell University	
EAS2550 Satellite-Based Remote Sensing — Rowena Lohman	Spring 2019 & 2020
EAS7800 Earthquake Record Reading — Geoffrey Abers	Spring 2019
Certification of Completion, Cornell University	
"Teaching & Learning in the Diverse Classroom" Course	Summer 2020
Guest Lecturer, Scripps Institution of Oceanography	
SIOG237 Space Geodesy — Yuri Fialko & David Sandwell	Spring 2017 & 2018
Graduate Teaching Assistant, California Institute of Technology	
Ge11d/102 Introduction to Geophysics — Robert Clayton & Mike Gurnis	Spring 2014
Ge161 Plate Tectonics — Joann Stock	Fall 2011
Ge263 Computational Geophysics — Jean-Paul Ampuero, Robert Clayton & Mike Gurnis	Fall 2012
Ae/ME/Ge266 Dynamic Rupture and Frictional Faulting — Nadia Lapusta	Spring 2011

#### STUDENT ADVISING/MENTORING

Segun Steven Bodunde(Ph.D. student at): Transient deformation in subduction zones, OU	2021/08-present
Haoyu Li (M.S. student at OU): Transient observations of crustal faults	2021/08-present
Ganiyat Shodunke (Ph.D. student at OU): Deformation at geothermal fields	2021/01-present
Gillian Quiros (UCSD Regents Scholar): Modeling nonlinear dynamical systems	2017/09-2018/05
Xander Zheng (Caltech SURF) (w/ M. Simons): InSAR analysis of LA basin aquifers	Summer 2012
Patrick Ferchaud (École Polytechnique) (w/ N. Lapusta): BEM modeling	Summer 2011

#### FIELD EXPERIENCES

Campaign GPS survey for the San Jacinto fault, Anza, CA, PI: Y. Fialko	Sept. 2016-2018
Rock sample collection and structure mapping of rock islands, Palau, PI: J. Kirschvink	Mar. 2017
Seismic deployment at Anza, PI: F. Vernon	Apr. 2016
Campaign GPS survey across central Taiwan, PI: SB. Yu, Academia Sinica	Dec. 2011
Seismic survey, Salton Seismic Imaging Project (SSIP), PI: J. Stock, Caltech	Mar. 2011

# PROFESSIONAL SERVICE & OUTREACH

Reviewer for proposals: NSF (ad hoc & panel), DFG (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft; ad hoc), NASA (panel), and USGS (panel).

Reviewer for journals: Geophysical Research Letters, Journal of Geophysical Research - Solid Earth, Geophysical Journal International, Earth and Planetary Science Letters, Bulletin of the Seismological Society of America, Earth Planets and Space, Earth and Space Science, Pure and Applied Geophysics, Tectonophysics, Remote Sensing, Geosciences, Energies, Sensors, etc.

Member, OU School of Geosciences Graduate Affairs Committee	2020-present	
Member, OU School of Geosciences Petroleum Geosciences Vision Committee	Fall 2020	
Member, OU School of Geosciences Computing Committee	2020-present	
Member, OU School of Geosciences Environmental Geophysics Search Committee	Spring 2021	
Founding Member, Inclusion, Diversity, and Equity in Earth and Atmospheric Sciences (IDEEAS)		
Working Group at the Cornell University	2019–2020	
Co-Leader of SCEC SEAS Working Group	2017-present	
Participant in Postdoctoral Leadership Program, Cornell University	2018–2019	
Outstanding Student Paper Award (OSPA) Liaison/Judge AGU Annual Meeting	2017–2019	
Organizer, Geophysics Seminar at IGPP/SIO/UCSD	2016–2018	
Organizer, Dix Seismological Laboratory Seminar, Caltech	2011–2012	
Board of Directors, Graduate Student Council, California Institute of Technology	2011–2014	
• Director at Large (2013–2014); Treasurer (2012–2013); Option Representative for Geophysics (Under-Represented Student Advocate (2011–2013)	2011–2013);	
Executive Committee, Caltech Chinese Students and Scholars Association	2010–2012	
• President (2011–2012); Director for Sports and Outdoor Activities (2010–2011)		
Outreach tour leader and speaker, Tectonic Observatory and Seismological Laboratory, Caltech	2010-2015	

#### **PROFESSIONAL SOCIETIES**

American Geophysical Union (AGU); Seismological Society of America (SSA); American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS); Society of Exploration Geophysics (SEG); Geothermal Research Council (GRC); American Rock Mechanics Association (ARMA).